A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Education, Media, Arts and Culture (EMAC) - Education, Knowledge, and Religion Unit (EKR), Office Files of Toby Alice Volkman FA712
Rockefeller Archive Center
The change in South Africa opened up many new opportunities to work in partnership with a range of South Africa partners to promote and sustain the transition to democracy. The Foundation supported women's groups working on law, development and reproductive rights. It contributed, for example, to the groups working on the Women's Chatter in South Africa, resulting in the adoption in 1994 of the first constitution anywhere that specifically included sections on women's rights.
During the 1990s, the promising political changes in African countries and elsewhere provided a positive perspective to counteract the continuing economic constraints facing the Foundation and the rising debt in developing countries. Both to reinforce local democratic initiatives and to address its economic challenges, the Foundation's field offices across Africa and the developing world shifted their support toward the promotion of smaller scale community-based initiatives.
Thomas supported work on arts and culture, not as a goal in itself, but, instead, as a means for promoting social justice, education, and human rights, both in the United States and in developing countries. At the same time, while reducing support for cultural institutions in the United States, such institutions received support overseas to preserve and celebrate national and local cultural heritages. While in South Africa, for example, the Foundation provided support for Johannesburg anti-apartheid theatre groups, in West Africa it funded for nearly two decades a program to preserve and make accessible cultural heritage by expand the training of museum leaders and strengthening museum exhibit and outreach capabilities.
In the early 1990s, the Foundation through its India office helped establish an independent foundation to enhance sustainability in the arts community. Ford envisioned new opportunities for cultural institution to rely on local resources focus on new forms of creativity and encourage young artists, in particular. Similar to the Indian effort, the Ford office in Egypt in 1993 provided support for an arts-focused foundation.
When Susan Berresford became president in 1996, with a strong commitment to globalization as well as concern for the uncertainty it created, she reorganized the Foundation in to three large program themes that would inform grantmaking in the United States and developing countries: Assets with a focus on poverty, Peace and Social Justice on rights issues, and Education, Media, Arts and Culture to pull together related endeavors. She also created a separate communications program. Each program was led by a vice president. Berresford strongly reinforced the institutional and grantmaking goal of affirmative action, an organizational goal that had been initiated in the Bundy era.
She maintained significant support, domestically and internationally for women's issues. She endorsed and encouraged the worldwide meetings staff members and grantees to continue to hold joint meetings in order to create a greater sense of partnership and shared purpose. The more promising international situation enabled the Ford Foundation in 1996 to open an office in Russia (Moscow) and in Vietnam (Hanoi). Berresford encouraged the development of local and regional peace and security programs in developing countries. A regional security, peace, and cooperation program in India, for instance, focused on the work of civil society groups as an increasingly prominent regional interest in South Asia.
In this period, the Foundation gave renewed the prominence of arts and culture in the US and maintained the commitment in developing countries. By 2000, funding levels for the Education, Media, Arts and Culture division were approaching parity with the other two, Assets and Peace and Justice.
Berresford also encouraged each of the programs to hold worldwide meeting to promote cross-program and cross-national collaboration in fields such as human rights, income generation, cultural preservation, and building capacity in the arts and arts management. One persistent question of such initiatives. Toward that end, and building on the earlier experiences in India and Egypt, Berresford worked closely with her senior vice president, Barry Gaberman and other staff to establish new foundations at the local and national levels, particularly in developing countries. Gaberman had been at the foundation since 1973, starting as assistant to the representative in Indonesia. After serving in a number of different positions, by 1984, under Thomas, he served as deputy vice president in the U.S. and International Affairs program. After the 1989, Thomas and Berresford appointed him deputy vice president. 1996, Berresford appointed him senior vice president.
As the twentieth century came to a close, the economic conditions of the 1970s and 1980s that had resulted in so much global debt, with special impact on the developing world, were slowly turning around. Many countries were experiencing economic growth and burgeoning democratic initiatives. Not only was the global economic situation improving but the Foundation's assets were also growing. Consequently, the Foundation was in a strong position to bring attention to long-standing issues holding back developing countries. The grants programs addressed the pressing need both for advanced training of young- to mid-career adults living in marginalized and disadvantaged conditions along the equally, and for strengthening and building sustainability of universities across sub-Saharan Africa, along with enhancing broadband access for improved internet communications, promoting women in higher education, and strengthening postgraduate education.
Reacting to the tragedy of September 11, 2001, the Foundation provided immediate relief to affected local institutions in the United States. The Foundation also helped launch support a fund at the Institute of International Education to support scholars at risk in countries in conflict and under terrorist threats, especially in, but not limited to, the Middle East.
Biographical / Historical
Segment 4. Period Summary - The Post-1989 Shift Away from Cold War Dichotomies
Franklin Thomas's presidency, lasting until his retirement in 1995, was defined by a commitment to connect the Foundation's US and international activities around a few key themes. These themes were addressed through grants that created private sector partnerships, enhanced support for local community groups, and enlarged initiatives to promote human rights, with special attention to women's rights. Throughout Thomas's tenure, Ford staff reinforced his special commitment to bolstering marginalized communities and broadening access to the law and educational opportunity. The Ford Foundation led the way in building the fields of international security studies, arms control, human rights, and governance. Moreover, in this period, Ford was innovative in drawing together the fields of international cooperation and human rights into one program.
Susan Berresford in her tenure as president from 1996-1997 continued and expanded the activities she helped initiate under Thomas. She and her colleagues increased support for the arts and established a variety of major international collaborative efforts implementing the concept of one foundation. Ford staff in this period drew on the Foundation's time-tested grantmaking strategies (supporting individuals and new institutions as needed), while concentrating on under-addressed issues and underserved populations. With Berresford's encouragement, Foundation staff explicitly took into account the new global context, increasing opportunities for inclusion of disadvantaged populations in all of their activities.
- Crossing Borders Initiative, 1997-2000; I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I includes grant proposals, applicant and grantee correspondence, proposal review notes, recommendations for grant action (RGAs), grantee narrative reports and internal memoranda. Two rounds of funding are documented: Round 1 grants made in 1997, and Round 2 grants from 1999. For a list of individual institutions/proposals contained in the "Rejected Proposals" folders (box 1, folders 41-44 and box 2, folders 24-26) see the grant RGAs.
  - Assessment, 1997-2000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Conference, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Conference transcripts, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - Initiative Announcement, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lists of Proposals, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Memoranda, 1997-1999 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Publicity, 1997-2000 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Round 1 – Grants – California State University, Dominguez Hills (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Round 1 – Grants – California State University, Los Angeles (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Round 1 – Grants – Colby College (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Round 1 – Grants – Dartmouth College (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Round 1 – Grants – Duke University (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Round 1 – Grants – Emory University (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Round 1 – Grants – Five Colleges, Inc. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Round 1 – Grants – Hamline University (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Round 1 – Grants – Hunter College (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Round 1 – Grants – Lewis & Clark College (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Round 1 – Grants – Middlebury College (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Round 1 – Grants – New Mexico State University (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Round 1 – Grants – New York University (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Round 1 – Grants – Northern Arizona University (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Round 1 – Grants – Oberlin College (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Round 1 – Grants – St. Lawrence University (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Round 1 – Grants – Trinity College (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Round 1 – Grants – University of California, Berkeley (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Round 1 – Grants – University of California, Humanities Research Institute (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Round 1 – Grants – University of California, Santa Cruz (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Round 1 – Grants – University of Hawaii, Manoa (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Round 1 – Grants – University of Illinois (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Round 1 – Grants – University of Iowa (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Round 1 – Grants – University of Michigan (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Round 1 – Grants – University of Nebraska, Lincoln (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Round 1 – Grants – University of Pennsylvania (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Round 1 – Grants – University of Texas, El Paso (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Round 1 – Grants – University of Virginia (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Round 1 – Grants – University of Washington (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Round 1 – Grants – University of Wisconsin, Madison (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Round 1 – Grants – Yale University (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Round 1 – Recommendation for Grant Action, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Round 1 – Rejected Proposals, A-C (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Round 1 – Rejected Proposals, E-K (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Round 1 – Rejected Proposals, L-N (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Round 1 – Rejected Proposals, O-S (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Round 1 – Rejected Proposals, T-W (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Round 1 – Request for Proposals, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Round 1 – Reviews, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Round 2 – Grants – California State University, Dominguez Hills (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Round 2 – Grants – Duke University (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Round 2 – Grants – Emory University (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Round 2 – Grants – Five Colleges, Inc. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Round 2 – Grants – Hamline University (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Round 2 – Grants – Middlebury College (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Round 2 – Grants – New York University (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Round 2 – Grants – St. Lawrence University (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Round 2 – Grants – University of California, Berkeley (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Round 2 – Grants – University of California, Humanities Research Institute (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Round 2 – Grants – University of California, Santa Cruz (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Round 2 – Grants – University of Hawaii, Manoa (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Round 2 – Grants – University of Illinois (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Round 2 – Grants – University of Iowa (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Round 2 – Grants – University of Michigan (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Round 2 – Grants – University of Nebraska, Lincoln (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Round 2 – Grants – University of Texas, El Paso (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Round 2 – Grants – University of Wisconsin (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Round 2 – Grants – Yale University (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Round 2 – Recommendation for Grant Action, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Round 2 – Rejected Proposals, C-H (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Round 2 – Rejected Proposals, N-O (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Round 2 – Rejected Proposals, T-U (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Round 2 – Request for Proposals, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Round 2 – Reviews, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Web Site, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- African Studies Initiative, 1995-1998; II
  Series II includes grant proposals, applicant and grantee correspondence, proposal review notes, recommendations for grant action (RGAs), grantee narrative reports and internal memoranda. Two rounds of funding are documented: Round 1 grants made in 1995-1996, and Round 2 grants from 1998. For a list of individual institutions/proposals contained in the "Rejected Proposals" folders (box 3, folders 22-24) see the grant RGAs.
  - African Studies Diversity Meeting, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - African Studies In Africa, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Round 1 – Grant Review, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Round 1 – Grants - Boston University (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Round 1 – Grants - Columbia University (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Round 1 – Grants - Emory University (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Round 1 – Grants - Howard University (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Round 1 – Grants - Indiana University (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Round 1 – Grants - Ohio University (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Round 1 – Grants - University of California, Berkeley (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Round 1 – Grants - University of Illinois (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Round 1 – Grants - University of Iowa (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Round 1 – Grants - University of Michigan (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Round 1 – Grants - University of Wisconsin (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Round 1 – Memoranda and Correspondence, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Round 1 – Recommendations for Grant Action, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Round 1 – Request for Proposals, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Round 1 – Selection Panel, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Round 2 – Grants – Clark Atlanta/Columbia/Howard Consortium (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Round 2 – Grants – Indiana University (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Round 2 – Grants – Michigan State University (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Round 2 – Grants – University of California, Berkeley (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Round 2 – Grants – University of Illinois (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Round 2 – Grants – University of Michigan (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Round 2 – Grants – University of Pennsylvania (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Round 2 – Memoranda and Correspondence, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Round 2 – Recommendation for Grant Action, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Round 2 – Rejected Proposals, C-E (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Round 2 – Rejected Proposals, H-I (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Round 2 – Rejected Proposals, O-Y (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Round 2 – Rejected Proposals, Reviewer Notes (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Round 2 – Request for Proposals, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Round 2 – Review Panel, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Other Grants and Subjects, 1982-2001; III
  Series III includes files on individual grants to support international and area studies programs that were not exclusively connected with the Crossing Borders or African Studies initiatives. Many are focused on Southeast Asian studies, a field of particular interest to Volkman. Also included are files on conferences, workshops and planning meetings where Volkman and her colleagues formulated their agenda to reinvigorate area studies. This material is complemented by copies of several of Volkman's "Reflection Memos."
  - African Literature Association, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Ambrica Productions – "China Emerges", 1995 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - American Council for Teachers of Russian, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - American Council of Learned Societies, 1982-2000 (Box 3, Folder 31-34)
  - American Council on Education, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - American Forum for Global Education, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - American Historical Association, 1998-2000 (Box 3, Folder 37-38)
  - American Museum of Natural History – Constructing Cultures, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - American Museum of Natural History – National Center for Science Literacy, Education and Technology, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - American Studies Research Centre, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Archives, Editing, Public History and Curriculum Development, 1996-1998 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Area Studies Librarianship, 1996-1998 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Asia Fellows Program, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Asia Society, 1993-1998 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Asia Studies in Asia, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Asia Studies, miscellaneous, 1996-1999 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Asian and Western States Initiative, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Asianetwork, 1995-1999 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Association of Professional Schools of International Affairs, 1995-1997 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Association for Asian Studies, 1998-1999 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Barnard College, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Bernstein, Alison R. – correspondence, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Board of Trustees – Education, Media, Arts and Culture Committee, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Board of Trustees – Meeting, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Brown University, 1994-1999 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Center for Arabic Study Abroad, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Center for Research Libraries, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Center for Transcultural Studies, 2000-2001 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - City College – Latin American Studies, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - City University of New York Graduate Center – Center for Place, Culture and Politics, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - City University of New York Middle East Studies, 1999-2000 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Columbia University – Center for Comparative Literature and Society, 1999-2001 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Columbia University – Center for United States-China Arts Exchange, 1992-1999 (Box 4, Folder 25-26)
  - Columbia University – Council for European Studies, 1991-1998 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Columbia University – Institute of African Studies, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Columbia University – Oral History Research Institute, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Columbia University – Restructuring International Programs, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Community College Humanities Review, 1994-1997 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Cornell University, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Council for the Development of Economic and Social Research in Africa (CODESRIA) – Northwestern University – Transcending Boundaries, 1991-2000 (Box 4, Folder 33-35)
  - Council for the Development of Economic and Social Research in Africa (CODESRIA) – Yale University – African Agrarian Studies, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Cultural Studies, 1995-1996 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Culture and Natural Resource Management – General, 1994-2000 (Box 5, Folder 3-7)
  - Culture and Natural Resource Management – Mozambique National Dance Company, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Culture and Natural Resource Management – University of California, Berkeley, 1996-1998 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Culture and Natural Resource Management – University of Florida – Conservation and Development Forum, 1994-1996 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Culture and Resources – Recommendations for Grant Action, 1988-1995 (Box 5, Folder 11-12)
  - East-West Center, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Eastern Seaboard Association of Tertiary Institutions, 1998-2000 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Education and Culture Initiatives, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Educations, Arts and Culture Consultative Group, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - European Association for South-East Asian Studies (EUROSEAS), 1995 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - European Science Foundation, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Facultad Latinoamericana de Ciencias Sociales (FLACSO), 1996 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Five Colleges, Inc., 1997 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Florida International University – Cuban Research Institute, 1995-1998 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Fulbright Educational Exchange Program, 1997-1999 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Gallatin Institute – Writers on the Range, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Georgetown University, 1995-1996 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - German Marshall Fund of the United States, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Grants as liaison, 1995-1997 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Gulbenkian Commission, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Harvard University – Asia Center, 1997-1999 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Harvard University – Center for Literacy and Cultural Studies, 1995-1996 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Inherited grants, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Institute for Advanced Study in Berlin – Literature and Culture in North Africa, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Institute for Intercultural Studies, 1996-1998 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Institute of International Education, 1993-2000 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Interdisciplinary Workshops/Seminars in Area Studies and Social Sciences, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - International Center for Migration, Ethnicity and Citizenship, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Japan Foundation, 1996-1999 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Joint Fund for International/Area/Cultural Studies, 1995-1998 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Kazanjian, Miriam Alexis, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Latin American Studies Association, 1996-1999 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Laurasian Institute, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Leadership Alliance, 1995-1999 (Box 6, Folder 3-5)
  - Lewis & Clark College – Asian Studies, 1999-2000 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Linguistic Diversity, Access and Opportunity, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Michigan State University – South Africa collaborations, 1998-2000 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Modern Literatures of Southeast Asia, 1992-1995 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - NAFSA Association of International Educators, 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - National Centers for Tolerance Education, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - National Council for Eurasian and East European Research, 1999-2000 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - National Council for Research on Women, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - National Council of Area Studies Associations, 1989-1996 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - National Foreign Language Center, 1986-1999 (Box 6, Folder 16-21)
  - National Foreign Language Center – National Organization of Less Commonly Taught Languages – University of Maryland, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - National Resource Centers, 1994-1999 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - National Security Education Program, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - New Approaches to Area Studies, 1996-1997 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - New School University, 1998-1999 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - New York University – Asian/Pacific/American Studies Institute, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - New York University – Center for Media, Culture and History, 1992-1999 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - New York University – Hemispheric Institute on Performance and Politics, 1998-2000 (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
  - New York University – Internationalizing the Study of American History, 1996-1998 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - New York University – School of Education, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - New York University – Yari Yari Conference, 1997-2000 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Northwest Regional Consortium for Southeast Asian Studies, 1995-1997 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Northwestern University – Melvile J. Herskovits Library, 1998-1999 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Nyae Nyae Development Foundation, 1988-1993 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Pacific Basin Institute, 1996-1997 (Box 7, Folder 10)